American Association of University Women, Bloomington Branch records, 1907-1997 C209
Indiana University Archives
American Association of University Women, Bloomington Branch records
1907-1997
1940-1989
Indiana University Archives
American Association of University Women. Bloomington Branch (Ind.)
C209
4 cubic feet 4 boxes
The American Association of University Women, Bloomington Branch was established on 12 February 1913 as the Association of Collegiate Alumnae with 60 charter members. They later became the AAUW in 1921. The goal of the group was to improve the status of women in higher education and to debunk myths concerning women academics. This collection is comprised of correspondence, financial records, governance files, meeting notes, reports, and scrapbooks. The collection also contains numerous subject files including those relating specifically to the Bloomington branch, and those relating to the Indiana and national divisions of the organization. These files contain materials on the history of the organization, various programs, committees, membership, conventions, and publications relating to the organization.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Advance notice required.
Administrative History
The national organization known as the American Association of University Women was founded in 1881 to promote the expansion of women's opportunities in education and employment. Established in Washington D.C. as the Association of Collegiate Alumnae, the organization sought to combat prejudices against women in academics and in the workplace by publishing studies debunking myths about the "damaging" effects of education on a woman's health and by exploring women's opportunities in traditional and non traditional careers. The organization also raised money for the funding of fellowships for women to pursue advanced degrees and to conduct research.
Today, membership is open to anyone who holds a bachelor's degree from a regionally accredited institution. The A.A.U.W. has a membership of 150,000 individuals with approximately 1,500 branches nationwide. The organization conducts business on many fronts including education, international relations and politics. The A.A.U.W. consistently endorses legislation that promotes women's opportunities in the workplace and academic settings such as Title IX, the Higher Education Amendments of 1986 and the Civil Rights Restoration Act. In 1981 the A.A.U.W. established the Legal Advocacy Fund for the financial assistance of women seeking to combat sexual harassment and sex discrimination in the workplace. The A.A.U.W. also established the Education Foundation to fund research and fellowships for university women and the Eleanor Roosevelt Fund, expanding their focus to include K-12 Education.
By 1987 the organization extended its membership to include men holding college degrees. Today, the organization continues to support women's education and employment efforts through financial assistance, research, and the promotion of legislation to combat all forms of discrimination.
The installation of a branch of the American Association of University Women was delayed in Bloomington, as Indiana institutions went unrecognized by the National Organization until 1912. A woman's eligibility was governed by her school's acceptability under the national organizations guidelines which called on institutions to provide students with a variety of course offerings and diverse library holdings, while at the same time maintaining membership in national organizations, and equal pay rates between the male and female faculty. When Indiana University finally gained acceptance under the A.C.A.'s, as it was then still known, guidelines activity to establish a Bloomington Branch commenced. The Bloomington Branch of the A.A.U.W. began 12 February 1913 under the name of the Association of Collegiate Alumnae, and the branch changed its name accordingly when the national organization of the A.C.A. adopted the title of the American Association of University Women in 1921. Sixty women signed on as charter members of the Bloomington Branch, mostly young women who had recently received their college degrees. They originally met every second Wednesday of every month in the Student Building. In the early years of the group, they were unable to raise money for substantial fellowships, but did sponsor an annual essay contest through the English Department for university women, and also sponsored a discussion contest that awarded nominal prizes to cover the cost of books.
By the 1940s and 1950s the branch had a more solid foundation and was able to raise more funds, sponsor international fellowship recipients and conduct community based fundraising efforts. The Bloomington Branch remained active throughout the 1960s, 1970s, and 1980s, promoting community involvement, educational diversification, and women's occupational issues. The Bloomington Branch of the A.A.U.W. always stayed politically involved, pushing forward important legislation for the betterment of women's experiences in education and the community.
Throughout the years the Bloomington Branch was active in the Indiana Division, the Great Lakes Region, and the A.A.U.W. national organizations, with four of its branch members going on to become Divisional Presidents. Also noteworthy was one of the Bloomington Branch's charter members, Nellie Showers Teter, who became Indiana University's first woman Trustee.
The Bloomington Branch of the A.A.U.W. was disbanded in July 1996.
Arrangement
The collection has been organized into three series: Administrative files, Subject files, and Scrapbooks.
Scope and Content Note
With materials which date from 1907 through 1997, the contents of the American Association of University Women collection is comprised of three series: Administrative files, Subject files, and Scrapbooks.
Series one, the Administrative file series (1916-1997), is comprised of five subseries: Correspondence, Financial records, Governance files, Meeting notes and Reports. Correspondence (1916-1997) includes incoming and outgoing correspondence that organized chronologically and according to the correspondence. Financial records (1949-1996) includes materials such as budgets, receipts and reports. The third sub-series, Governance files (1925-1993) is comprised mostly of bylaws and charters of the Bloomington Branch and the Indiana Division of the A.A.U.W. The Meetings notes (1939-1996) sub-series contains board meeting agendas and minutes, branch meeting minutes and bulletins, secretarial materials, and State Board meeting minutes. The fifth sub-series, Reports (1937-1992), is composed primarily of Annual Reports, Branch Reports, and Treasurer's Reports. Correspondence written by and addressed to Indiana University President, William Lowe Bryan, has been removed and filed in his presidential collection under the heading "A.A.U.W." Correspondence to or from William Lowe Bryan after he resigned as president of the university (June 1938) remain in the collection.
Series two, Subject files (1907-1996), are organized alphabetically by folder title. These files include branch histories, information on programs, calendars, fellowships and scholarships, membership information, A.A.U.W conventions, and several publications. The newsletters are arranged chronologically with the A.A.U.W. Bloomington Branch Newsletter running from 1969-1985. The newsletter was re-named the Bloomington Leaf in 1985 and in this collection the span continues through 1992.
Finally, Series three, Scrapbooks (1941-1988), contains the Scrapbook materials of the Bloomington Branch, and is comprised mostly of newspaper clippings cut from the Bloomington Herald Telephone and the Indiana Daily Student from the 1940s through the 1970s.
Photographs from this collection have been transferred to the Archives Photographs Collection. Please ask a member of the Archives staff to see them, if interested.
Separated Material
Photographs transferred to the University Archives Photographs Collection.
Correspondence written by and addressed to Indiana University President, William Lowe Bryan, has been removed and filed in his presidential collection under the heading A.A.U.W. Correspondence to or from William Lowe Bryan after he resigned as president of the university (June 1938) remain in the collection.
Acquisition Information
Part of collection donated to the Indiana University Archives by Betty Yoder and Dolores Lahrman, Accessions 0401 and 98/042. Accessions 7193 and 7194 added to the collection in 2008.
Women college graduates --Indiana --Bloomington --Societies and clubs --History --20th century --Sources.; Women educators --Indiana --Bloomington --Societies and clubs --History --20th century --Sources.; Universities and colleges --Alumni and alumnae --History --20th century --Sources.; Feminism and education --Indiana --Bloomington --History --20th century --Sources.; Women --Education (Higher) --Indiana --Bloomington --History --20th century --Sources.; Graduate woman.; Leader in action.; Bloomington leaf.; Newsletter (American Association of University Women. Bloomington Branch (Ind.)); American Association of University Women. Bloomington Branch (Ind.) -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; American Association of University Women. Bloomington Branch (Ind.) -- Archives; American Association of University Women. Bloomington Branch (Ind.) -- Records and correspondence
- Administrative files, 1916-1997
  - Correspondence, 1916-1997
    - General (Box 1)
      - 1920-1980s (Box 1)
      - 1923 (Box 1)
      - 1924-1925 (Box 1)
      - 1935 (Box 1)
      - 1937-1943 (Box 1)
      - 1945-1947 (Box 1)
      - 1951-1956 (Box 1)
      - 1979-1980 (Box 1)
    - Arpan, Holly, 1984-1986 (Box 1)
    - Bruner, Marjorie A., 1996-1997 (Box 1)
    - Greenleaf, Betty, 1966 (Box 1)
    - Holmsted, R.W., 1937 (Box 1)
    - Kinker, Kandace Libka, 1970s (Box 1)
    - Loose Correspondence, 1979; undated (Box 1)
    - M.E. Dodds Scholarship Thank-You Notes, President's Copies, 1980-1981 (Box 1)
    - Old Membership Correspondence, Joy Chamnes, 1916-1921 (Box 1)
    - Pesyna-Newman, Kim, 1980s (Box 1)
    - Vogt, Mary, 1985 (Box 1)
    - Yoder, Betty, 1986-1989 (Box 1)
    - Yoder, Betty, Correspondence with Richard Lugar, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Financial records, 1949-1996
    - General (Box 1)
      - 1955, undated (Box 1)
      - 1978-1979 (Box 1)
    - AAUW Budgets (Box 1)
      - 1963-1970 (Box 1)
      - 1967-1986 (Box 1)
      - 1986-1989 (Box 1)
    - Dues, 1986-1996 (Box 1)
    - Financial Logbooks (Box 1)
      - 1920-1927 (Box 1)
      - 1949-1963 (Box 1)
    - Paid Bills, 1968-1972 (Box 1)
    - Remittance Transmitals, 1970-1973 (Box 1)
    - State Treasurer Remittances, 1967-1968 (Box 1)
    - Transmittal Reports Slips, 1959-1970 (Box 1)
    - Treasurer's Materials, 1980-1989 (Box 1)
    - Treasurer's Receipts and Reports, 1963-1967 (Box 1)
  - Governance Files, 1925-1993
    - Arpan, Holly-Resolutions, 1984 (Box 1)
    - Bill for an Act to regulate child age in schools, 1955 (Box 1)
    - Bylaws and Charter (Box 1)
      - (selected years), 1925-1969 (Box 1)
      - 1941-1946 (Box 1)
      - 1973 Revision (Box 1)
      - 1979 Revision (Box 1)
      - 1981 Revision (Box 1)
      - 1983 Revision (Box 1)
      - 1985 Revision (Box 1)
      - 1985-1987 (Box 1)
      - 1987-1989 (Box 1)
      - 1991-1993 (Box 1)
    - Elected Branch Officers, 1954-1958 (Box 1)
    - Indiana Division Branch Presidents, 1950-1951 (Box 1)
    - Indiana Division Directory and Bylaws (Box 1)
      - 1942-1955 (Box 1)
      - 1968-1973 (Box 1)
    - Not-for-Profit Status, 1954-1985 (Box 1)
    - Tentative Legislative Program, 1941-1947 (Box 1)
  - Meeting Notes, 1939-1996
    - General, 1940-1969 (Box 1)
    - Arpan, Holly (Box 1)
      - Agendas, 1985-1986 (Box 1)
      - Minutes, 1985-1986 (Box 1)
    - Binder, 1939-1940 (Box 1)
    - Board Meetings, 1985-1989 (Box 1)
    - Board Meeting Agendas (Box 1)
      - 1979-1981 (Box 1)
      - 1985 (Box 1)
      - Lessing, Joyce (secretary), 1987 (Box 1)
      - Nolan, Susan (secretary), 1988-1989 (Box 1)
      - Simpson, K. Brooks (secretary), 1987-1988 (Box 1)
      - Yoder, Betty (secretary), 1984-1985 (Box 1)
    - Board Meeting Minutes (Box 1)
      - 1977-1981 (Box 1)
      - 1985-1986 (Box 1)
      - Charbonneau, Sharon (secretary), 1981 (Box 1)
      - Kamman, Ann (secretary), 1981-1984 (Box 1)
      - Lessing, Joyce (secretary), 1986-1987 (Box 1)
      - Nolan, Susan (secretary), 1988 (Box 1)
      - Simpson, K. Brooks (secretary), 1987-1988 (Box 1)
      - Yoder, Betty (secretary), 1984-1985 (Box 1)
    - Board of Directors Minutes, 1942-1943; 1953-1954 (Box 1)
    - Branch Bulletins, 1940-1943; undated (Box 1)
    - Branch Meeting Minutes (Box 1)
      - General, undated (Box 1)
      - 1927-1932 (Box 1)
      - 1933-1939 (Box 1)
      - 1944-1954 (Box 1)
      - 1954-1955 (Box 1)
      - 1980-1981 (Box 1)
      - 1984 (Box 1)
      - 1984-1988 (Box 1)
      - 1985 (Box 1)
      - Lessing, Joyce (secretary), 1986 (Box 1)
      - Simpson, K. Brooks (secretary), 1988 (Box 1)
    - Convention Committee Minutes, 1981 (Box 2)
    - Executive Committee Minutes (Box 2)
      - 1953 (Box 2)
      - 1981 (Box 2)
    - Program Meeting Minutes, 1981-1982 (Box 2)
    - Secretarial Materials, 1979-1981 (Box 2)
    - Secretary's Book, Bloomington AAUW (Box 2)
      - Part 1, 1985-1990 (Box 2)
      - Part 2, 1990-1996 (Box 2)
    - State Board Meeting Minutes (Box 2)
      - 1953-1955 (Box 2)
      - 1955-1957 (Box 2)
    - Supplements to Minutes, 1983-1985 (Box 2)
  - Reports, 1937-1992
    - Annual Historian's Report, 1949-1954 (Box 2)
    - Annual Reports (Box 2)
      - Bloomington Branch (Box 2)
        - 1944-1946 (Box 2)
        - 1984-1986 (Box 2)
      - Indiana Division (Box 2)
        - 1952-1953 (Box 2)
        - 1970-1973 (Box 2)
    - Branch President's Reports (Box 2)
      - General, 1939-1957 (Box 2)
      - Blish, Louise, 1973-1975 (Box 2)
      - Bruner, Marjorie, 1981-1984 (Box 2)
      - Lockridge, Mrs. Ross F. (Elsie) (Box 2)
        - 1942-1943 (Box 2)
        - 1943-1944 (Box 2)
      - Robinson, Una, 1941-1942 (Box 2)
      - Zietlow, Ruth P., 1979-1981 (Box 2)
    - Branch Reports (Box 2)
      - 1938-1939 (Box 2)
      - 1984-1989 (Box 2)
      - Jackson, Lillian, 1937-1938 (Box 2)
    - Report of the Committee on Graduate Women, 1939 (Box 2)
    - Report of the Committee on Women's Education, 1950 (Box 2)
    - State Report on International Relations, 1952-1953 (Box 2)
    - Treasurer's Reports (Box 2)
      - 1946, 1950-1966 (Box 2)
      - 1967-1978 (Box 2)
      - 1978-1986 (Box 2)
      - 1986-1992 (Box 2)
      - Cogswell, Judith (treasurer), 1965-1966 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous reports (Box 2)
      - 1942-1944 (Box 2)
      - 1946-1955 (Box 2)
- Subject files, 1907-1996
  - 30th Anniversary, 1943 (Box 2)
  - 50th Anniversary, including Cecilia H. Hendricks review of branch founding, 1962-1963 (Box 2)
  - 100th Anniversary-Women in Higher Education, "IU Night", 1952-1953 (Box 2)
  - AAUW Fellowship Song, undated (Box 2)
  - Agreement, 1970-1980s (Box 2)
  - Arpan, HollyBranch Materials, 1983-1986 (Box 2)
  - Art Exhibits, 1945-1946 (Box 2)
  - Arts Committee Art Program, 1941 (Box 2)
  - Branch Report Form, 1979-1980; undated (Box 2)
  - "Building A Yellow Brick Road"A Blueprint to Branch Success", 1979 (Box 2)
  - Calendars, 1987-1989 (Box 2)
  - Calendar / Yearbooks (Box 2)
    - 1926-1947 (Box 2)
    - 1948-1953 (Box 2)
    - 1954-1959 (Box 2)
    - 1960-1965 (Box 2)
    - 1966-1975 (Box 2)
    - 1980s (Box 2)
  - Clippings, 1937-1974; undated (Box 3)
  - Community Participation, 1985 (Box 3)
  - Conferences, 1966-1967 (Box 3)
  - Contributions, 1921-1926 (Box 3)
  - Cultural Interests, 1981-1982 (Box 3)
  - Education Committee, 1937-1939 (Box 3)
  - Educational Foundation Program (Box 3)
    - General, 1980-1989 (Box 3)
    - "Names Honored" Booklet, 1974-1975 (Box 3)
    - Project, 1986-1987 (Box 3)
  - Eleanor Roosevelt FundTeacher Endowment Sabbaticals (TES), 1988-1989 (Box 3)
  - Fellows (International), 1968-1969 (Box 3)
  - Fellowships/ Scholarships (Box 3)
    - 1937-1975 (Box 3)
    - 1966-1985 (Box 3)
  - Fundraising (Box 3)
    - Christmas Cards, 1986-1987 (Box 3)
    - Flower Mart, 1969-1970 (Box 3)
    - H.M.S Pinafore, 1969 (Box 3)
    - Historic Homes Tour, 1966 (Box 3)
  - FYI Officers, 1985 (Box 3)
  - "Graduate Woman" (Box 3)
    - 1985-1986 (Box 3)
    - 1986-1987 (Box 3)
    - 1988 (Box 3)
  - Grants, 1985 (Box 3)
  - Historical Round-ups, 1913-1943 (Box 3)
  - History (Box 3)
    - 1907-1962 (Box 3)
    - 1913-1969 (Box 3)
    - 1914-1985 (Box 3)
    - 50th Anniversary, 1962 (Box 3)
    - 50th Anniversary Speeches, 1962 (Box 3)
    - 70th Anniversary, 1982 (Box 3)
    - 75th Anniversary, 1987 (Box 3)
    - Bloomington Branch, 1988 (Box 3)
    - Indiana Division, 1949 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous, 1980-1989 (Box 3)
    - Sponsorship and Organizing New Branches, 1923 (Box 3)
    - Undergraduate Grant Program, 1917-1970 (Box 3)
  - Indiana Division "Bulletin" (Box 3)
    - 1935-1945 (Box 3)
    - 1945-1989 (Box 3)
  - Indiana Division Fact Sheet, 1961 (Box 3)
  - International Relations, 1930-1939 (Box 3)
  - International Federation of University Women, 1924-1926, 1953 (Box 3)
  - "Leader in Action", 1987-1989 (Box 3)
  - "Leader Links", 1987-1988 (Box 3)
  - Legislative Programs, 1969-1971 (Box 3)
  - Loan Fund, 1936-1937; undated (Box 3)
  - Maps, undated (Box 3)
  - Materials, 1923-1924; undated (Box 3)
  - Meeting Activities (Box 3)
    - General, 1980s (Box 3)
    - Footprints, undated (Box 3)
  - Medicare Law Fact Sheet, undated (Box 3)
  - M.E. Dodds Scholarship (Box 3)
    - General, 1984 (Box 3)
    - President's Copies, 1980-1988 (Box 3)
  - Members (Box 3)
    - Berry, Lillian Gay, 1960s (Box 3)
    - Dodds, Mary Elizabeth (Libby), 1984 (Box 3)
    - In Memoriam, 1980s (Box 3)
    - Shalucha, Dr. Barbara, 1915-1985 (Box 3)
  - Membership (Box 3)
    - Applications, 1960-1980s (Box 3)
    - General (Box 3)
      - 1935-1936 (Box 3)
      - 1988-1989 (Box 3)
    - Lists (Box 3)
      - 1917-1971, undated (Box 3)
      - 1933-1941 (Box 3)
      - 1938-1941 (Box 3)
      - 1994-1996 (Box 3)
    - Materials (Box 3)
      - 1980s, undated (Box 3)
      - 1969-1989 (Box 3)
    - Membership Booklets, 1951, 1967-1969 (Box 3)
    - Membership Procedures, 1938-1940 (Box 3)
  - Morrison, Sarah Parke, 1919-1984 (Box 3)
  - National Conventions (Box 4)
    - 1925-1969 (Box 4)
    - 1953-1967 (Box 4)
  - National Women's History Project, 1986-1989 (Box 4)
  - "News Flashes", 1940-1941 (Box 4)
  - Newsletters (Box 4)
    - Annual Membership Tea Newsletter, 1975 (Box 4)
    - "Bloomington Leaf" Newsletter (Box 4)
      - 1985-1987 (Box 4)
      - 1987-1992 (Box 4)
    - General, 1965-1983 (Box 4)
    - General, 1969-1974 (Box 4)
    - General, 1981-1985 (Box 4)
  - Northeast Central Region Biennial Conference, Indianapolis, IN, May 1942 (Box 4)
  - Notices, 1967-1968 (Box 4)
  - Officer Materials, 1988-1990 (Box 4)
  - "Outlook", 1989 (Box 4)
  - Pamphlets (Box 4)
    - "After College", 1942; undated (Box 4)
    - General, 1937-1943 (Box 4)
    - Research Service, 1940-1941 (Box 4)
  - Poster (Box 4)
    - Exhibit and Consignment Space, undated (Box 4)
    - Indiana History Poster, undated (Box 4)
  - Posters to Schools Project, 1988 (Box 4)
  - Program Materials (Box 4)
    - General, 1934-1945 (Box 4)
    - Sample Programs, 1950s (Box 4)
    - Vice President, 1984 (Box 4)
  - Projects (Box 4)
    - General, 1922-1947 (Box 4)
    - Biographies of Indiana Women, 1985 (Box 4)
    - Women's History-Lilian Gay Berry, 1943 (Box 4)
  - Questionnaires, 1980s; undated (Box 4)
  - Questionnaire Results tabulated by L. Dillman and Anna Gillum, 1968 (Box 4)
  - Regional Conference, Chicago, IL, May 6, 1966 (Box 4)
  - Regional Meetings, 1942-1956 (Box 4)
  - Scholarship Fund Information, 1917-1954 (Box 4)
  - Script - "Fellowship, Faith and Funds" - written by Blanche Wellons, 1957 (Box 4)
  - "Short-Changing Girls" and "Hostile Hallways", 1992 (Box 4)
  - Social Studies Materials, 1935-1937 (Box 4)
  - Speakers and Visitors, 1942-1945 (Box 4)
  - State Conventions (Box 4)
    - 1923-1972 (Box 4)
    - April 1955 (Box 4)
    - April 1956 (Box 4)
    - May 1957 (Box 4)
    - 1966-1967, 1987 (Box 4)
  - Trading Post, 1963-1968 (Box 4)
  - Treasurer's Instructions, 1960-1969 (Box 4)
  - War Services, 1940-1942 (Box 4)
- Scrapbooks, 1941-1988
  - Clippings, 1960-1980s (Box 4)
  - General (Box 4)
    - 1963-1967 (Box 4)
    - 1971-1977 (Box 4)
  - Newspaper Memorabilia, 1981-1985; undated (Box 4)
  - Publicity (Box 4)
    - Clippings, 1964-1987 (Box 4)
    - General, 1980s (Box 4)
    - Lockridge, Mrs. Ross F., 1942-1944 (Box 4)
    - Photographs, 1988 (Box 4)
    - Robinson, Dr. Una (President), 1941-1942 (Box 4)